[Music]
hey folks
welcome to the dark horse podcast i have
the honor of sitting today with greg
lukianov
who is president of fire the foundation
for individual rights in education
and co-author with jonathan height of
coddling of the american mind
he is also i believe the recipient of
the 2008
playboy freedom of expression award is
that correct greg
yes well done it was a it was an
honor um if you read coddling you might
have heard that i had a pretty rough
2007 and i was pretty
in a pretty big low and getting that
really helped
i could you used the moral support in
2008.
but it did not require the production of
any photographs that you now fear being
released or anything like that
this is a christy hefner runs a lot of
the um
the free speech awards and i actually
was pleased to hear
uh a elderly recipient of one of the
awards um
say what the rest of us were thinking
it's like why don't we get invited to
any of the fun playboy part
it was it was very upscale very very
respectable almost to the point of being
like
mildly disappointing got it
all right well there's so much to talk
about i don't hardly know where to start
yeah business is booming you might have
missed it
right um how are you enjoying the
collapse of western civilization is it
going about as you expected
luckily um given my family history uh
and you know my my father was born in
1926 in yugoslavia his father then died
when he was six
and i've always had that to compare
myself to you know it's kind of like
am i an orphan with ricketts in
yugoslavia in the 1930s
about to be killed by slalom or nazis
yeah but it's
i mean and the thing is like i don't
usually say
very over-the-top things but like i
tweeted in the past six months this is
this is as bad as i've seen it like i i
i would have
i would have thought if you had told me
five years ago even though we were way
ahead of the curve on talking about free
speeches on campus and
um runaway ideology i would still
think you were making stuff up because
it is everything has gone nuts
well that's very interesting to hear you
say that i i should say i uh
i get a lot of credit for having
predicted what was going to happen
but you and and jonathan height were
well ahead of me
in terms of predicting this and to hear
that you are surprised
i must say um i i can't be terribly
surprised at what has happened but i'm
certainly surprised at the speed with
which it is happening
exactly so in an original article in
2015 we were predicting that there was
going to be an increase in anxiety and
depression
and you know we thought it would be a
modestly measurable
you know little thing on a graph it's
like oh see here it's a
we're talking about uh you know graphs
that go off uh up like hockey sticks
when it comes to mental health so
basically we saw a lot of this stuff
coming we didn't expect it to come like
next year
yeah it's uh it's interesting i wonder
what it
is that sounds like caused us both to be
caught off guard by the speed what is
is there an accelerant in here that we
might have
might have perceived if we had looked at
it um you know definitely social media
has sped
everything up it's sped up polarization
it spread up sorting it sped up mental
health issues you know we
we argue in the book at least but
definitely i'd say trump
um i i feel like the uh
the ridiculous political era we're in
has sped up
all the pro all of the uh political
processes we talked about in cuddling
the american mind
because one of the things we did did say
that was one of the reasons why
generation z was so different was
because the polarization
politically was hotter than ever and
that just went
um through the roof in 2016.
yeah it really did go um through the
roof now
you of course focused in coddling
on the degree to which online dynamics
do amplify these processes so that
didn't
uh come out of nowhere that that was
definitely a big part of your
model and i did write something in 2014
uh called freedom from speech
which talked about how i think that um
as other
and the thing is you know ultimately in
a lot of ways i'm a i'm a steve pinker
optimist
i i would rather live now than 100 years
ago
you know i'm excited about space
elevators and carbon nanotubes and all
the all
and having nanites in my blood and all
that kind of stuff um
but one thing that i i did want to add
some nuance to
the argument of things getting better
which was really almost like there was a
sugar high in the early part of the
uh of the teens um
that there are some things that get
worse precisely because other things are
getting better
so technological advantage advancements
that let you live
um in communities that reflect your
values or even find those communities
even if you don't live close to them
you know that that sounds lovely um but
also as
you know everything from you know uh
psychoactive drugs that
that decrease pain frankly we're having
what i call in the book a problem of
comfort that essentially we're in
you know self-reaffirming groups both in
our real lives
um physically we've moved to more uh
isolated
areas and online they pat you on the
back for that
and my argument in freedom from speech
was that essentially
there's a category of things that will
get worse precisely because some other
things are getting better
and i do think the situation for free
speech as
things get worse is going as things get
better
technologically is going to get worse um
i think people become more not
non-compromising in a situation where
you know
500 people agree with me i can't be
wrong why why should i compromise on
this stuff
having to remind people that compromise
and democracy
is good so i want to run something by
you it's a model i've been
playing with and forgive me if i'm
reinventing something that you have
already described but i have the sense
that the online
environment that what we have in fact
seen is
a phase transition where we are now
dealing with a critical mass of people
for whom the
online environment is primary
and the online environment is of course
not actually primary but if you were to
mistake it as primary
it might result in certain dynamics that
i think we are now seeing unfold
so in short what i would say
is if i'm having a discussion with
evolutionary biologists
online if i'm in a chat about
evolutionary biology
presumably i have the right or we have
the right
to exclude young earth creationists it's
not that they don't have the right
to speak about young earth creationism
but if we are to have the ability to
talk about evolutionary biology anywhere
there has to be a place where we can
simply say actually we're not going to
entertain
young earth creationism here and so
that right whatever it is made of looks
to me
like it has been extrapolated to all
sorts of things where it doesn't
belong so for example uh
online we are told that if one
has any skepticism about the claim
that a man who declares himself a woman
is in fact a woman upon that declaration
if we have any doubts about that
then we are we are turfs we are trans
exclusionary radical
feminists and therefore we have
committed a sin
a grave right wrong yeah a grave moral
wrong and we are to be driven out
and so i have the sense that this i mean
it's obvious nonsense i'm a biologist i
know that
the fact that you may declare yourself
female doesn't make you female and that
you know we might
agree that that's the way you should be
treated but it doesn't change certain
underlying biological realities
nonetheless if you imagine that
people see the internet as a space in
which they are allowed to establish this
rule in the same way that i as an
evolutionary biologist might establish
the rule
that young earth creationism is isn't to
be discussed in this you know
in this subreddit or whatever that you
would get this behavior where the point
is you have to exclude those who violate
the rule in order that the conversation
can progress as normal i i think there's
a lot of truth to that and it's actually
it is a lot where my head is about two
to two different things
um the first is that one of the reasons
why i think things have gotten so hot
in 2020 in terms of hyper polarization
and ideology
run wild is that because of covet
because we're home all the time
we have become our avatars we've become
our online personality
24 hours a day and without face-to-face
contact without the
you know the rigmarole of daily life um
people in their avatars
they're uh much less reasonable they're
much more ideologically pure they're
much braver of course because you're not
actually um you're not actually facing
uh people so i think that
that we're seeing the distortion of what
hap because at first i remember like
during covet it was kind of nice to see
everybody online you know it was like
the
and we all spent way more time online it
was like hi everybody how are you doing
there was this kind of honeymoon period
and then that weird kind of spiral of
of ideology took over but here's here's
here's the least
probably popular or on pc thing i'm
probably going to say
is that i feel like what's happened to
our entire society
is that tactics for winning arguments in
dormitories in the night
and and and in departments in the 1990s
have become treated as if they are
the law of solomon um that that
essentially you know
any dissent from uh from theories of
privilege
um any dissent from theories about uh
sexuality
they're serious about sexual identity
that's just a great moral sin
um and that doesn't have to be have to
be discussed but all these things they
weren't meant to actually be true
they were supposed to give you a
rhetorical advantage in arguing but you
know if you do assume
they're 100 true i mean that was one of
the reasons why you know and
this goes beyond what fire does but why
i was concerned about the 1619 thing
is because the the 16 19 argument the
argument that it's all was only ever
just about slavery and nothing else was
something that you would hear
on campus sometimes and it was you know
uh debated uh as as it should be
but then it just got treated suddenly
just in the past couple
of what was it was it was that this year
that that came out uh
i believe it was about a year ago a long
year wow
yeah so but that argument got
being treated as if it was gospel fact i
was like wow okay we've really
we've really we these arguments have won
but not not because they're true because
they're rhetorically useful
and taken for granted by a a certain
group of
former college students or current
college students
well i wonder if our models are about to
converge here because
um the way i would they sound like they
could
yeah i think i think they're headed in
this direction so what what i'm
imagining
is that people from
our generation and uh am i right
gen x yes
yes we should we should those of us who
still remain
in this tiny generation should gather
for a reunion at some point but
absolutely
um so what i'm imagining is that people
from
our generation and those above are
misunderstanding something about the
arguments that are being
deployed because they come couched
as arguments about matters of fact which
is very confusing
right but in fact what i suspect they
are
is gambits in a negotiation
that in effect if you take my model that
basically there is a
a generation or several generations now
that
are playing with the idea that the
online environment is in fact
in some sense deeper truer more real
and you know i can still man that point
although it's obviously wrong in the end
but right
if you imagine that people are
proceeding from that starting point
then there's a question about
establishing
the rules of that environment going
forward
and if you believe as i do and i would
presume you do that the u.s for example
is not perfectly fair with respect to
race that there are in fact
historical biases that echo through to
modernity then the point is well those
need to carry no weight
online right we can actually neutralize
them
yep for real and it's not that difficult
what we do is we set out the rules
by which online discussion proceeds and
you can see this in the case of the
gender question
because at some level if we're talking
about
how you are to be treated online if you
say you're a woman
you're a woman right that's plausible
online
it becomes implausible when you go to
see your doctor
right or when you commit a crime and we
have to decide which prison to send you
to
or we have to decide whether or not you
can enter a race in
a women's category rather than compete
against men
but online there's no need for any of
those things to be relevant we
can just simply decide the sexes are
equal
you are what you say you are let's go
and so we can neutralize issues of class
we can
neutralize issues of race we can
neutralize issues of gender
online and that when we are told
that uh if i say well no
there's an issue of gamete size that you
there's no amount of surgery that can
correct for it and it has implications
right i've just said something i don't
think it's controversial at a biological
level
but if i say that online then the point
is i have to be punished because i've
violated the proposed rule and that in
effect the vast pylon of people who will
call me a turf
are really basically enforcing
the new rules of how of essentially
etiquette of how we are to interact
in the online environment so
then the problem comes that the outside
world actually
is primary it is real and they wish to
export sure it's real
well if you're gonna push me to the
philosophy i'll say we cannot be
perfectly certain but it would be uh
it would be uh pointless to to worry
about it but
1619 is effectively the
online rules right in which we are to
treat we have been told that we are to
treat the united states as if
it was exclusively about slavery that
that was
100 of the project we are to treat that
as real
i would argue as some sort of
compensation right that there has been
a historical blindness to the importance
of slavery
and so now there's going to be a
compensatory over emphasis that's the
rules of the online environment but
they're now being exported into the
world we're now going to teach them to
children as fact
yeah right rather than them being the
rules of the discussion online
yeah and one last wrinkle on it is the
uh place
that uh i you know heights
uh his primary area of scholarship is on
what's called moral foundations which
i'm sure you know all about
and you know when we were working on the
book i was asking are you saying that
this
some of this ideology is an analogous to
religion or is taking the place of
religion and he says
it's taking the place of religion flat
out um and that's that
that so some of these rules that because
they have this sort of
moral heat behind them that basically
your brain is supposed to shut off if
they're violated
it really like like the word used before
it really does
have all the markings of of sin
yeah it does and then i would uh add
my evolutionary wrinkle to uh to your
work and john's work here and i would
say the problem is that it is
functioning
as a literal religion but without the
one thing
that religion brings to the table that
makes it more or less safe
forgiveness and mercy uh no but these
would be downstream products of that
it would be the fact that whatever
religion if it's a true religion
right it's long standing right so you
know it's not riddled with fatal errors
it may be riddled with untruths oh nice
okay yeah i get it
so at some level what we're facing are
is the invention of a new religion and
there is no one alive who can tell you
it doesn't end in gulags or gas chambers
or starvation
or you know nuclear exchange we don't
know what happens because this one is
you know it's a prototype yeah and you
know it's playing with all of the most
important tools we're watching
it sweep through you know governance
which means that suddenly
you know the nuclear regulatory
commission is dealing with the question
of whether or not
you know presumably fission
is a process born of white supremacy or
who knows what
right so that's very dangerous oh yeah
and it's kind of funny because i mean
we're both left-leaning people
and and that's and we you know i i used
to work at this program called the
environmental project in the 90s we
worked with inner city high school kids
to do environmental justice work
um and i've i got all my democrat
friends together back in 2003 to say
listen
really what we should be focusing on is
energy
and to see you know my side of the
spectrum actually saying
um we care about new we care about um
global warming but we want to get rid of
fracking and no nuclear
it's like are you serious about this and
and that gets treated like it like an
article
uh like an article of faith and we're
all arguing
with the same kind of one-upsmanship and
and grandstanding that people
argue in dorms yes now you and i might
come out different places
on fracking and fission
i don't know but yeah nonetheless i'd
love to be spending
astronomical amounts of money on fusion
um to be clear oh me too
that that's exactly where i think we
should be investing and it's possible
that we
need some upgraded kind of vision to get
us there because we don't know when
right and just for now it's better than
the other options
and we're not gonna we're not gonna get
to where we need to be but the but
really i think we should be spending
apollo project type money on fusion
i agree i've i have argued we need a
manhattan project for fusion
um because it's actually the one it's
the one technology
that i think plausibly saves us going
forward that said
i think if we do if we invented it today
if it got announced this afternoon
it would make things worse not better
yeah i can actually think of a lot of
ways or at least we'd just
figure out a way to argue ourselves out
of it i mean this this has already
started happening with some of the um
uh super carbon materials like that i
got excited about you know like i was
amazed at how fast people were talking
about you know the potential of
particulate matter
you know to to um be very harmful to
people's lungs
but as if that's why we shouldn't pursue
it it's like this could be this could
change everything this gives a
you know um if we have this can't we try
to figure out
that issue you know later well we and
i don't know it's like the precautionary
principle that they have uh
you know currently in the european union
which is just which is just a formula
for
stagnation and not being able to fix any
of the problems you currently have
well so uh heather i have a book that
will be coming out
uh next year oh tell me and it is going
to
include in it the argument that we need
some
version of the precautionary principle
but that the problem with the
precautionary principle is that
everything depends on how you
instantiate it because
if you instantiate it narrowly you're
right you
bring everything to a halt because you
can't be totally certain of the safety
of anything
sure um so anyway there's a i think
there's a more sophisticated way
um to pursue it but yes it is something
we would have to
agree to broadly and in fact
you know you're an interesting person to
be talking to about this because
uh it is i think clear to both of us
that we are actually watching a very
dangerous breakdown in civilization
that is in some ways the downstream uh
consequence of new technologies whose
danger we didn't anticipate
do you mean you mean specifically social
media
well i mean you know social media
i mean feed algorithms
search algorithms i mean focus
groups and the ability to predict
behavior
and to modify it with sophisticated uh
propaganda all of these technologies
have caused a
um a breakdown in our sense-making
and in our sense of allegiance to each
other and that's
that's obviously at one level the root
of the problem which i think is
uh part of the argument you deploy in in
coddling
yeah um so how do you square that
with your sense about the precautionary
principle was there a place where we
needed to look at
what was unfolding and say wait a minute
this could be
so dangerous that we have to put the
brakes on it in some way um
you know if we had a precautionary
principle for social media like
let's say that was part of the culture
already social media still would have
gone ahead because
really people didn't see any harm in it
it's like oh you show cap pictures and
hey you get pat on the back for
um for what group you're in i i think i
think even a strong version of that
still would have led to the existence of
twitter and facebook and
um the sorting algorithms
and of course you know since i'm a civil
liberties guy um you know i think in
terms of um
my biggest fear of course is is
centralized power um
and so when i was working on the book
with height when we were finishing up
our recommendation sections for social
media you know he he definitely had a
lot more faith in top-down
um solutions but i know what top-down
solutions are going to look like it's
going to be you know the president of
princeton uh shouldn't pick on princeton
actually no they did the job you
the professor pat's thing was actually
pretty bad um and it always turns out to
be whatever is in the interest of power
um that's the thing that gets banned and
people say please
have more censorship to protect the
downtrodden it's like yes we'll take
that and now i'm going to shut up my
critics
you know it is the way it works so my
hope is that we start developing um
cultural norms around
use of social media i think that's
really the only way out is
is some process of developing norms
around
i i feel like i've seen some glimmers of
reasonability
in little enclaves on twitter or on
facebook for example
maybe i'm just completely uh completely
spoiled um
so i i don't think there i i think that
the precautionary
principle wouldn't have known far enough
into the future what the downside would
have been meanwhile
i you know and this is something i've
been saying for a long time but i still
really think it twitter is the closest
to looking at the way
um the human mind works of probably any
technology that's ever been
developed and what's better is or
better in the sense of more interesting
is that it's immediate and it's for
hundreds of millions of people so it's
kind of like looking into the collective
unconscious of the entire species
and if that doesn't get people excited
as a research opportunity you know it's
one of the reasons
nicholas christakis and i have been
friends ever since
actually since well before the incident
at yale
but he gets really excited about this
stuff too and and there's so much to
learn
about human nature and tribalism and
that kind of stuff
from this technology um if we can just
survive its initial
impact i feel like we're in the period
you know sometimes people will say oh
luke lukianov and height you know
people said the same thing about the
printing press and it's like you you
chose a bad example there yeah
because it led to you know hundreds of
years of religious war um became pretty
much directly out of it
so i think right now we're in the
religious war i just hope it's not
hundreds of years
right or fatal to the species that would
be bad that would be unfortunate
um but all right so this is this is
interesting
you are you are hostile to the idea
of um structures that would be
and i agree would be abused by people to
shut down their critics i mean we're
already seeing
this um i i would challenge your sense
about a view into the collective
unconscious
okay great because i believe twitter
would be that
if twitter were an unmanaged platform
so it's more like the superego now no
since there's so many
powerful norms it's just the way we talk
it is downstream of many things but one
of them
is twitter's perverse incentives yeah
you're right right and so the problem is
it's like
a glimpse into the unconscious of a
propagandized person
right we are a propagandized population
and therefore
what we think on twitter is
heavily edited not just by our
distorted fear of a pylon right
right the fact that a hundred people
piling on you in an ugly way
is enough to dissuade you for from
saying something when in fact 100
or for leaving the house right
exactly but the point is the the way
people pile on
and the way people have now organized
themselves to pile on more effectively
to modify what gets said is a distortion
of
the view into the unconscious and then
there's twitter's
obnoxious policy of deciding
um you know for example that
um covid19 that sars cove
ii is inherently
that the consent the scientific
consensus that it is a natural virus
that emerged
from bats is so secure that we can
declare
anything that doesn't adhere to this
consensus
as um a kind of
um unforgivable thought that it will
label things
yeah right um what that does is it tamps
down
the fact that you've got lots of people
who are looking at
the facts even just the basic facts and
saying that doesn't add up and there's
this other
hypothesis that does add up and it
doesn't seem like we know enough to know
which origin it has yeah so well and
that's what it's kind of funny kind of
the gateway drug to censorship in a lot
of cases are
conspiracy theories and i take two
different approaches to that as being a
free speech person who isn't
particularly
bothered you know by this is one even if
they're false conspiracies move the
world and it's important to know what
people really think full stop
this this is this is my free speech
radicalism it comes down to something
very simple
it's always important to know what
people really think period
and so for example like we would have
such a poor understanding
of of where the anti-semitism came from
before world war ii if we didn't
understand
the the uh protocols of zion it'd be
being this huge
you know uh uh fraud and hit
but understanding like people's paranoia
and superstitions all of the stuff
it is is um is so incredibly important
but also the other part is there's
always a possibility that it could be
true
um and i mean given you know my family
had to flee the soviets you know um
it's just one conspiracy after the other
so this is funny brett
that this room doesn't think i'm here so
i occasionally have to do this
[Laughter]
well um maybe you should just take up uh
gesticulating as a more
central part of your communication
modality oh i'm actually really tamping
it down right now
this is the one that i seem to do for
everything according to my wife
uh it's it's an atom or the galaxy
or you know like there's so many things
that actually it's like well this is
going to happen and it's like
yeah i do it without even realizing it
it's arguments in 2020
yeah right there's a certain roundness
to that argument
there is a certain that was a favorite
law school professor uh said that one
time
trying to be nice um but but i thought
that was great
so let me uh take you back to two things
you just said here
cool um one i want to talk to you about
conspiracy theories
yes um because i feel like we're missing
the boat on this one
okay great there is a very obvious way
to deal with conspiracy theories and
that is not to traffic in them
right but there's a way to deal with the
possibility of true things
and it just so happens that we have the
most excellent system you could possibly
want for dealing with them which is
science
so i uh want to be very clear and i have
been very clear with my audience
that theory has a precise meaning that
means it has withstood
rigorous tests there should only ever be
one theory at a time
right that is to say the theory of
natural selection is the theory of
natural selection because we have so
thoroughly
tested it and there is no competitor
right before it was tested it was a
hypothesis
and so i would say the responsible way
to deal with the conspiracy issue is to
say
these are hypotheses the fact that one
advances a hypothesis doesn't mean you
even believe it's true
right you can have all kinds of
hypotheses this you know
our conversation could be taking place
in
a simulated universe i don't believe
that's true but i do regard it as a
hypothesis
and to the extent that it makes
predictions it's testable so
so i think the point is we have been
sold a bill of goods we've been led
into a dangerous territory by
thinking in terms of conspiracy theories
when in fact they are hypotheses they
make predictions and we can treat them
exactly as seriously as you would
a proposed scientific idea that hasn't
been tested or
has you know given mixed results well
here's why you get in trouble
brad thought experimentation
devil's advocacy are absolutely
essential to the production of ideas
and i say this stuff on campus and
people are like what people have to take
the other side of different arguments
i'm like
yeah actually ideally you'd have someone
who actually believes the other side of
the argument because they're going to
know the most arguments for it and
they're going to be able to
they're going to be able to um to defend
it but if not someone in your team
should pretend
that they are willing to throw out these
other hypotheses on what actually
happened
and i'm seeing i'm seeing a situation on
campus
where that's been sort of obliquely
threatened
and now it's being very directly
threatened we just had a case of st
john's
where a prophet do you know do you know
this one brett i don't think so
this is a this is a case where a
professor was um in a history class was
talking about
um the colombian exchange you know the
uh all the wonderful things that the
rest of the world got
from columbus's uh quote-unquote
discovering the new world
and of course that includes things as
basic as potatoes and tomatoes like
that alone would have made it an
incredibly important
exchange but this is a serious
historical question kind of like for all
the horrors that came out of the
um the triangle slavery and all this all
the the um
uh and and the murder and the exposure
to smallpox and all these horrible
things the question is you know was it
worth it
any serious intellectual any serious
student should be able to go
huh you know and and puzzle through that
and come down be able to come down on a
side
but it's treated in this case so much
like heresy
that the professor was suspended um
at st john's and i think this i think he
still is um he was relieved from
teaching
and and i'm seeing more and more cases
because a lot i saw a ton of cases for
years
whereas professors saying something on
twitter that would get them in trouble
absolutely a free speech issue
absolutely important but it's moving
closer and closer to the classroom
although you might know something about
that well yes i
it does seem to me i encountered
something a few years back i'll see if i
can remember what it was
yeah but okay so i totally agree with
this thought experiment
is an essential tool right and the
ability to voice a thought experiment
even an obnoxious thought experiment
right is part and parcel of how
you know we do moral philosophy among
other things i mean trolley problems
right if you couldn't talk
trolley problems because you're killing
innocents well then you know you're
robbed of this important uh tool for for
the advancement of uh
of ethics yeah but um okay so
we um well i wanna i wanna take you back
to that second thing before we
lose the thread sure sure so you are
very skeptical about top-down
solutions to our online problem you
agree that we are
dealing with very dangerous downstream
consequences of technologies that we
couldn't foresee the hazard
yeah as they were invented so that some
sort of precaution were it possible
might have saved us from that but maybe
no
conceivable precaution could have
existed um but here's the question
isn't the solution for online an
upgrade to our
constitutional protectionists that have
worked so well for speech in other
realms
so like what would that look like well i
think it would look like exactly what
you have just described which is a
radical
commitment to keeping the space open to
ideas
including obnoxious ones because the
consequence of trying to shut it down
and leaving only respectable ideas
is unthinkably terrible on very short
time scales
yeah and that's been that's been my and
people like david french's argument that
essentially if you're going to
start regulating speech guess what you
have this absolutely brilliant body and
and i'm i'm the obnoxious american my my
mother's british slash irish my father
grew up in yugoslavia but as russian
um and you know you're taught from a
pretty early age not to go over there
with
thinking your values are superior but i
totally break that norm when i go to
other countries and talk about first
amendment
because i and and i have and what i
explain is i know you guys think we're
nuts but
in this country you know any practically
any country in europe
you're going after speech because it
someone finds it offensive
in our country one of the major
differences between us and everybody
else
is actually relatively small but it's
that we have a bedrock principle that it
can never be
merely because someone finds it
offensive that doesn't make cultural
sense that
these norms change from period to period
they're different from from economic
class economic class from nation to
nation from men to women that it
in some cases so the principles that
actually are
have been thought out by frankly some of
the best minds um in
in us history i mean you know oliver
wendell holmes and
louis brandeis were no were no slouches
on this stuff
and that it presents this really
sensible body of of of law
um and actually philosophy and how you
actually deal
deal with speech and i think that would
be ideal um
way to regulate speech to use those
standards regulate speech on the
internet
i can't quite bring myself though to
want to give up the freedom of
association
and expressive rights that these
companies have in the first place
but i do think that if there was if
there was a place that actually
applied these rules um it would be and
applied them very
uh very firmly it would be a healthier
environment for one
um even though there'd be some nastiness
of course to be expected
but the direction that um twitter and
facebook are currently going
i think that it's going to start looking
like the absurdities that you see
uh in in europe and and worse it's going
to also
involve things and and you know one of
the reasons why nobody wants to even do
the thought experimentation what if this
actually was a biological weapon well
because of the power
wealth and influence of china well
that's true
i should say just point of clarity
that it was a biological weapon is a
hypothesis it means oh no it's
production
and i assume that and the funny thing is
i know people on the on the interwebs
would would be like well
he claimed this and i'm like yeah no
it's a i i totally understood his
hypothesis it's a hype well that wasn't
the one
that so i personally believe um the most
robust hypothesis we don't have a theory
of its origin yet we really don't know
but the most robust hypothesis
is a lab leak but not a weapon yeah this
was
a virus that had picked up
capacities through what's called gain of
function research
and then escaped presumably it infected
a
a worker and would have gotten out that
way um though that's not the only path
but
in any case these are competing
hypotheses
right i haven't seen any support yet for
the
bio-weapon hypothesis though it's a
hypothesis whether there's any evidence
for it or not the point is
right were it true it would it would uh
make certain predictions about the way
it behaved
well the whole time bomb aspect of it
the ability to um transmit
asymptomatically and then you get wallet
by it
um you know two weeks later is that's
clever
and that's definitely one of the reasons
why i think people think it you know
sometimes go to
it being a weapon is it's just so
perfectly designed to spread
well i would say that's not a prediction
though that is an observation
of its nature which leads to the
hypothesis right it
could be a bio weapon in which case it
would have to have other
features but but in any case i guess
my only point is it just so happens that
we have
the most robust system ever devised
i believe the most robust system
possible for figuring out what's true
and it's already the bedrock of western
civilization
why do we exclude conspiracies from
its application why do we leap to
calling these things theories rather
than start with the idea that their
hypotheses
you know and you know to your point
about thought experiments
the beauty of this system is that it is
a formal feature of it that the fact
that you are
advancing an explanation for something
and positing
predictions that would come from that
explanation has nothing to say about
whether you believe it's true
right in fact when you're working
scientifically the right thing to do is
to generate as many hypotheses to
explain an observation as you can
and then test to see which of them is
correct which means that you've got
simult you've simultaneously advanced
mutually exclusive ideas that's part of
the
part of the nature of the work and so if
we simply brought the discipline
of this hypothetical deductive thinking
to
questions of conspiracy and collusion
we free ourselves from the madness that
happens when
you know even voicing a conspiracy is
now taken to be an embrace of it
and that is taken to be a sign of some
sort of mental failure
yeah well and that's what i was getting
at by saying you know
what your problem is kind of jokingly
but it does seem that
so much progress comes from us um
trying to get into our prefrontal cortex
you know basically kind of like
putting our assumptions to one side and
trying to actually bring it forward
based on evidence and that kind of stuff
um but it's really important to remind
everyone you know like that there's a
reason
why you know rational thinking was a
radical idea
when it was proposed you know by by
greek thinkers or or buddhist thinkers
you know for example the
the discernment you know as it's called
in the buddhist buddhist tradition
because everything about human beings
you know
almost everything pulls us against it
we're superstitious we're tribal
uh we're we're not good seeing our own
biases and blindness
all this kind of stuff but which also
you know it's just
a little digression but it's something i
care a lot about it's funny in these
arguments that you see on campus is you
can see
things that basically say we only
recently discovered this thing
called bias and by bias they mean
prejudice um
and that's kind of amazing though that
they put in the language of bias because
it's kind of like what do you think
the constitution's about what do you
think separation of powers is about what
do you think
all of these things were partially
because we were lucky enough to be
founded as a country during a period
where there was a lot of rational
thinking about how
badly and well we make decisions and
therefore splitting things up and having
checks and balances and all this kind of
stuff abs absolutely brilliant
well so when you said earlier that um
you depart from the the norms
by advocating for the idea that
uh our principles are superior i'm not
shy about this i mean and to me it seems
like another
empirical question i mean on the one
hand it is certainly true
that our system was counter-intuitive
on its founding and has spread yeah
right
people have seen what it does and they
have embraced it in large numbers
yes so that suggests something about it
i would also argue that you know you to
say whether it is superior or not
one has to identify a criterion that you
are
or several criteria that you are trying
to maximize
but i think it would be hard to do
better than
realized liberty right that to the
extent that a human being is
a fantastically capable creature
that can engage in insight innovation
compassion the creation of beauty and
all of these things that
it's wonderful when a system liberates
us to do that
and that therefore there is some basis
to judge our system
and um to the extent that there are
others out there that
do very well on uh those
evaluations most of them are um
building on the prototype that was set
up here yeah
yeah and it's interesting because i've
always been as someone who's like a big
fan of david hume and a lot of the
scottish enlightenment i've always been
um
pretty hard on the romantics and i think
that a lot of the evil
of the world came out of the the post
you know the post enlightenment period
and i still think that
however um i have developed a little bit
of a soft spot in my heart
you know for what it must have been like
for those early days of liberty that
basically kind of like what
what can i see about the beauty and
complexity of the world and about my own
nature
if i'm freed from a narrow expectation
of religious expectation of what
every single person in the world should
be like and i i get at an emotional
level how powerful that must have been
and interestingly at the same time geez
interestingly at the same time we got to
learn more about human nature because of
that so it ended up being this
interesting feedback loop the
rationalists keep on kind of studying
but once they actually see what a full
flowering of humanity could look like
with everybody from
you know walt whitman to oscar wilde
einstein
um we in this co-relationship of liberty
and learning
we got to learn a lot more about human
nature absolutely
now here i i actually have no idea what
you'll think of this but
my sense yeah well we'll see about that
so my sense is that the
founding structures of the u.s were
an absolutely brilliant prototype
flawed in many ways sure but every
prototype will be
cynical and pessimistic at the same time
cynical and optimistic at the same time
sorry
well uh they had the correct tensions
identified for the most part
they couldn't possibly have anticipated
the technological world
that these protectionists would need to
to function in and so in some sense i
have the feeling
that as brilliant as the founding
documents are
that they are inadequate to our
modern puzzle that they point the right
direction to what problems we should be
trying to solve
but for example i think the founders
were
keenly aware of the danger of
um of malignant governance
they were not nearly frightened enough
of
the kinds of scaling effects that the
internet would bring about and the fact
that the kinds of power that they feared
might not be in governmental hands at
the point that
um we faced the next battle with them
that they would be in private hands
which i think is the problem that you
were grappling with a moment ago about
well
but but but to be clear in defense of
the of the founders one of the things
that they added besides
um tremendous optimism about human
nature and realism and pessimism about
what we're actually liking groups
was flexibility was the ability to
actually change it and that's something
that you know no religion
you know would would allow for it is
like well we're kind of assuming we're
not right about everything and that that
epistemic humility they had from the
beginning
we're going to make it hard to change it
but it's not impossible uh to change it
to adapt to new uh
to new to new changes so they basically
anticipated the fact that they couldn't
possibly have known everything
um and uh allowed for changes just they
had to be
yeah it had to jump through a serious
hurdle and
what is on us is that we're too partisan
divided to actually be able to
you know um to make any of that those
kind of
uh super majority type situations
they're basically impossible into the
current environment all right
two points one uh i agree with you about
their far-sightedness with respect to
building in a self-correction
mechanism i still think we may have
outstripped the capacity of that
mechanism
at least as it's understood and that
there's a huge danger so i think
i you know we do effectively need
the upgraded constitution but we dare
not open the process that would create
it because it would be
a disaster if we would get so many
stupid things
got the dumbest amendments you've ever
seen in your yeah so
so the mechanism is uh is not up to the
challenge of modernity
but i do want to point out you might
wanna are you sitting down greg
better okay good now you could stand up
but you might want to hold on to
something because what i'm about to say
is so mind-blowing
that uh it could result in a
disequilibrium
the religions also have an update
capacity but it's an it's an
evolutionary one
and so for example martin luther uh
nailing the 95 theses on the church door
results in a um well what in biology we
might call a speciation event
what in uh computer science we might
call a forking event
right and basically it creates a new
version
of christianity which then forks into a
bunch of different versions of
protestantism
and the point is sectarian disagreements
over how things are to be understood
what traditions are to be held which
ones are to be jettisoned
that is the fodder that selection
functions
on and what we see is
religions are constantly in battle to
figure out
you know you know does your version of
christianity
listen to the pope or not right you can
keep your catholicism
but you jettison the pope and you become
you know the greek orthodox church or
something like this
so become american catholics well
american and that would be one of many
different versions
where you know the book is the same
atheist by the way raised catholic just
uh
i'm picking on my own people you're
picking on your own people then it's
it's
it was at least forgivable until five
minutes ago i don't know if it's still
within the rules
but uh but in any case yes the update
mechanism is different
in the constitutional case the founders
gave us
a conscious mechanism for intentionally
changing
the structure in the religious case what
we have is an evolutionary and
unconscious mechanism for update um but
i would argue they amount to something
very similar mm-hmm
interesting yeah i i like it um have you
have you had jonathan rausch on your
show no not yet he's coming out with a
book um that's
awesome and i'm totally jealous of it
it's called the constitution of
knowledge and
you know like the some of the stuff that
you were describing before it just made
me think of his theory of liberal
science
um just the idea um and i think it
deserves theory rather than the
hypothesis in this case uh just just the
idea that
the enlightenment produced a system for
uh deciding things it's not quite the
scientific method actually you could
kind of include the scientific method as
a subpart of liberal science
um and it's you know something that he
wrote in his 1993 book kindly
inquisitors
um but he's really expanding on that now
and he's
and what i like is he's taking on both
um
you know uh academia and journalism you
know
with a left-facing uh threat but then
the epistemic disaster
that is the trump administration um uh
and he's he's taking it from both
directions i've got i've gotten to read
some of it so far and i think he'd love
it awesome
well uh so i'm now speaking without
knowledge of the topic on which we're
we're talking but i would say uh it
sounds
i would argue that we have the
scientific method
but that method is embedded in a larger
method
which you might call liberal science
yeah and
the fact is many features of that larger
informal
agreement are essential for it to work
well
in other words nowhere in the scientific
method will you see
the process by which um we
uh innovate our way out of a cul-de-sac
right it's not captured there it's
captured in
the habits of mind and discussion
amongst the sorts of people who become
fixated on
the way fields get stuck right and so
getting a field
unstuck is an unruly process in which
you
entertain all sorts of outlandish
possibilities
most of which are simply wrong and you
then
end up finding some sort of uh path out
of uh
your off your local optimum onto a
higher peak yeah
so anyway yes i i would love to see if
somebody has
captured that and uh described it
properly i would love to see this sort
of expanded scientific method
understood well because frankly it only
does you so much good to teach students
you know uh observe or hypothesize
predict
test right that's part of it for sure
but it ain't the whole thing
by a long shot no absolutely not
yeah so all right if we um maybe switch
topics just a little bit can i ask you
uh you and i met in must be late 2017.
does that sound right it was at the uh
fire
um the fire professor conference
yeah the fire professor conference who
was our speaker was that was that alex
trigger
uh yes it was alice baker she was great
i was a man
it was a great talk you know what came
out of that conference by the way brett
um
there were two professors there um
one was italian one was spanish and they
were so inspired by how lively it was
and then they also you know they also
really stumbled on mayan heights work
and got really excited about it
and they invited me over to a conference
in italy
um i thought just to be on a panel and
then i found out that they had made this
giant
like um exhibit you know based on
and i was like completely floored i'm
like are we like
are we big in italy suddenly like it was
so
the fact that the the the spirit of the
of the fire
professor um conference gets people all
riled up just makes me
it just makes me very happy yeah well it
was it was a great conference
um and i can absolutely see if somebody
wasn't deeply
steeped in your way of thinking them
showing up at that conference and
uh being stunned by it makes makes
perfect sense to me
um let me ask you though
so you and jonathan height had
done your initial article and you were
already
thinking very deeply about the hazard of
what was taking place on college
campuses and you had formulated the idea
of
igen the basically the internet
generation and the fact that they were
cognitively seemingly quite different
from the generations that had preceded
them
at some point the evergreen
debacle happened yeah
do you remember this was before we knew
each other
do you remember your encounter
with that material and what you thought
in light of what you had
already imagined was taking place this
uh and your debacle that was uh the
spring of 2017
right it started may 23rd of 2017
just before 10 in the morning wow um
i remember uh hearing about it and by
that point i was so
shocked and sad and jaded because you
know the milo riots which we cover in
some detail in the book i don't care
what you think about milo yiannopoulos
but that was insane
and then we had you know the wonderful
alison stanger assaulted
you know defending a professor she
disagrees with at middlebury
he had the surrounding of the
uh of the place where heather mcdonald
was speaking um at claremont mckenna
and so basically like when that started
happening to you
um i was already so sad and cynical um
but yeah i remember that being
especially outrageous
and wanting to and it's interesting
because sometimes the cases that are the
most spectacular
are the ones that fire gets very
cautious around because there just seems
to be too many moving parts and we're
very serious about making sure we had
our
facts straight and honestly brett your
case was really hard to keep track of
how many freaking things were happening
at the same time i mean
if there was there was like except i i
use it um actually now
in my slideshows to talk about you know
i talk about the different threads that
create problems on campus i talk about
legal issues i talk about
polarization issues i talk about uh you
know things related to social justice
and then at the very end i actually put
yours and saying and by the way all of
these things were happening at the same
time in the brett weinstein case
yeah it um so i i you know i don't know
that it was
um the most uh what word did you use
i don't know i forgot what word you use
something to the effect of it being the
most dangerous i don't know that it was
i think it
it certainly was um the most
colorful and i you know it's interesting
to hear that
it was kind of comprehensive because it
it just included
you know because you even had sort of
backlash from right wingers you had
you know administrators showing acting
like administrators it was
it was it was like a symphony yeah it
had it all i think i think benjamin
boyce is actually writing a musical
about it which i think will be it's
it's the perfect way to do it i think
but um
but yes it was it it was all inclusive
it had all of the
the layers and the it had an obsession
with um documentation
mm-hmm right so i remember the canoe
meeting
yes yes the wonderful canoe meeting so
that is the one of the weirdest
saddest it it and and the administration
in so many cases they acted
really like and i don't mean this i mean
this in very literal sense like children
or like cult members who have been
reduced to this
infantilized state
but as i was sitting in that meeting i
was having this
this uh i wouldn't say despondent but it
was next door to the feeling of this
despondent sense
because i didn't think i was going to be
able to explain
the absurdity of the situation to anyone
right i thought that it was going to be
impossible for me to
even i was even concerned i wouldn't be
able to explain it to heather right who
was only
a couple blocks away at the time and i
realized that they
evergreen had these very fancy they had
basically a television studio
and they were recording the meeting
and i thought oh no they're going to
record it but they're going to realize
how bad this makes them look and they're
not going to release it is there
anything i can do to force them
to release it right and i was pondering
that question
and it turned out nope they didn't
realize at all what they had
filmed and they put it out and it was
like well
thank goodness at least now i don't
sound like a crazy person yeah right
because it actually happened they caught
the whole thing
yeah yeah i had a similar situation
because i i was on a videotape nicholas
christakis
um you are that was me yeah
um in in the solomon quad wow
leading by the way to like horrifying
kind of like conspiracy theories like
how did greg luchanov end up in this and
it's like well it's pretty simple
um uh erica who i adore
and and nicholas had invited me to speak
there um i just
it's true i ended up in the middle of a
firestorm kind of kind of shocked
and so i i was videotaping it and the
reason why i released it
was because there was at least a dozen
other people videotaping it including
the yale daily news
um and they should forever be ashamed of
themselves
because i was told that night by someone
who worked for the news but was critical
of this that they were planning to
release the footage of the confrontation
in a way that will make nicholas look
bad and i was like
okay i guess i have to post my video now
so i
i posted the video showing him showing
you know um
absolutely amazing composure in the face
of such shoddy nasty treatment and
keeping in mind also they're coming
after his wife you know they were going
after his kids who were who
were there they asked his son
to sign a a denunciation of his mother
and he's still like somehow nicholas was
just amazing he he just uh he just held
it together
and so yeah for a very different reason
like they they they didn't
the yale daily news refused to put
anything up because they
they thought it made the students look
bad but of course it made them look bad
because
they were not behaving very well yeah no
it
revealed something it's not it's not
that it made them look bad i mean
yes and so this was the thing that was
completely missing at evergreen was
there was no awareness that what they
were
revealing was not the rest of the world
right it didn't need
anybody to editorialize about it it was
self-evident what was going on and it
had a lot of elements of
you know cult and bullying and uh
this really heavy coercion and obviously
you know so many things that were said
were just
completely at odds with the evidence so
um
thank goodness at least that it has
happened in a couple places where
i mean i guess wow what would the what
would the yale situation have looked
like if you had not captured that
yeah no it was yeah it would have been
hard to convey
um what was really going on there and
that was something that was
frustrating because for for years fire
had been
uh saying that you know students are
kind of
apathetic you know that they're not all
that politically motivated
and then you know we should have watched
what we asked for because we got it
um but so we suddenly have this
explosion
of student protest um in the in in the
fall semester of 2015. you know um
organized all around the country
um but then to you know we're like all
right cool protest i'm like
oh but they're demanding less free
speech they're demanding that this
newspaper be shut down that these
administrators be fired
and it was very clear that they were
following the pattern of you know
find a provocation no matter how
how how small or tenuous and then make
it
into a big deal and demand that you know
the umass newspaper be shut down or dean
spellman get fired or
nicholas christakis i mean and that's
the killer it's like that
those students didn't have a better
friend on campus than nicholas and erica
christakis they they were
truly the they're some of the best and
smartest people that i've ever met
um yeah and i think that one thing that
they weren't expecting though was the
fact that since you could actually see
some of this it didn't
it it didn't look as as good on film as
as they thought it did
or it did in the venues that they
you know if they were playing to an
online audience that they knew
then these looked like wins but they
couldn't help but it being broadcast to
a larger world that understood it was
way off yeah something like that
oh and while we still have some time i
did want to plug one thing while i'm on
here
oh please and i think he'll dig it um so
uh
one thing that fire really tries to do
is you know
we try to spread the good word of free
speech and due process and academic
freedom
but we try to also be creative about it
we're most known
for our uh for the individual incidents
cases where students get in trouble
and professors get in trouble and that's
our bread and butter so to speak but we
always try to do
more creative things so we did the
documentary can we take a joke
about canceled culture but made in 2015.
um we did you know freedom from speech
we did calling the american mind
which i'm really proud to say is still
reaching people but my former assistant
who's now the vice president of
communications because he's amazing um
went out and he's not a filmmaker went
on his own to make a documentary
specifically about the life and times
of ira glasser who was the head of the
aclu
right after skokie all the way up
through 2001
and it it it's amazing like the film
that they
that they actually made and this was
just a labor of love by non-filmmakers
but it
it it comes out i think today um and
it's i really recommend it to everybody
because it's really inspiring because
they show
they show someone who's politically
liberal who is willing to like debate
bill buckley even take bill buckley to
his first football
uh his first baseball game who talks
about the relationship between free
speech
and uh diversity and inclusion frankly
and in
in the uh in the context of jackie
robinson
and of course even being willing to
defend the nazis at skokie who by the
way you get to see
by them being revealed um they look like
absolute
like the absolute idiots they were if
they weren't allowed to you wouldn't
have known how ridiculous they look
there's a moment when when this idiot is
is organizing this nazi rally where he's
just kind of there's little things wrong
and it looks like he's just about to to
yell out you're turning this nazi rally
into a disgrace
like it's absolutely comedic when you
get to see what this guy looks like in
real life
but yeah it's called the mighty ira and
and we're really psyched about it
awesome i am definitely going to check
that out yeah
i must say it's not no surprise that you
and i would agree on this but yeah the
right
cure for uh obnoxious speech is to let
it be aired so people can see what it
actually
is and yeah unfortunately you know it's
very clear that this era in which
um censorship is back with a vengeance
uh is also an era in which we are losing
agreement on the most basic stuff you
know whether or not
two plus two equals four whether or not
men and women are different like we we
have lost
the ability to agree on anything and i
think people do not fully appreciate the
danger of that
yeah no i i it it worries me
um and yeah i remember when people were
saying
oh well you know when these students get
to the real world
that'll straighten them out and we're
definitely saying from the very
beginning it's like well no if there's
enough of them they'll change the real
world into a very strange place
and what's what drives me nuts is that i
hate and i have people who are
in charge of um all sorts of different
companies come to us
and say it's like listen we've got a
crop from this elite school
um or these elite schools and it's
dysfunctional
like things that used to be just
interpersonal tensions have turned into
immediately going to human resources and
then like almost
complete parallelization of some
organizations but they always say
but you can't say what's what
organization this is um but it's going
to bring
it's going to bring organizations down
it probably already has
you know what happened at the um at the
new york times with james bennett that
was absolutely
this dynamic you know definitely there
were older uh older people as well who
were against him
but the whole dynamic of just the um you
know if it's
if we can call you make a strong
argument that somehow this is
and of course they rhetorically use the
this is threatening our lives
argument which is the ultimate
rhetorical uh card you can play
to get rid of a uh editor who was
specifically hired
to try to rock the boat back in 2016 um
it's th this summer i hope that i
feel like the fever is starting to break
a little bit at least this current fever
and that maybe things aren't as
illiberal and scary as they were maybe
in say august
but it's going to come back at some
point if we don't do
something about it well it's going to
come back and a lot is
riding on the election and it's not
clear that either
path actually addresses the issue but
um so
yeah it's interesting that you see it as
possibly the fever having broken i
certainly
hope that's the case i think we're in a
great deal of danger but
we uh we we are just that i i feel like
there is at least
um some amount of pushback that i'm
seeing where people aren't immediately
getting fired for saying
you know what would have once been
considered mildly controversial stuff
yeah so you said it's going to bring
down institutions
i think if anything you're being too
cautious that
uh at some level the game theory is very
very clear
and to the extent that you have
different if you had universities
with different commitments to wokeness
those that were woke
would fail because they would be
producing
inferior graduates who were less capable
of thinking clearly about all the things
that college is supposed to arm you
to think about but when every college
does it the point is
everything downstream of those colleges
is going to suffer those flaws which
means
that the private sector firms that
depend on those graduates
will be hobbled relative to any
presumably foreign competitors that
aren't
similarly hobbled so effectively you're
looking at everything
at the higher scales being jeopardized
simultaneously which
ultimately means the nation will be uh
rendered and capable of fending off its
competitors abroad which could
restructure
the way the whole planet functions and
frankly it could restructure
the level of commitment to liberty that
the planet has because
the u.s has been bedrock to that
commitment to liberty yeah that's really
funny you should say that because
that's exactly one of the things i'm
working on an article about right now
about how
just by having an increasing incidence
of actual
you know papers being withdrawn and and
research really being seriously caught
into question
at a time when higher education is
already there's already a lot of
skepticism about it because people are
realizing
they can do this stuff online they can
do this they can do they can do the
stuff at home and it's ridiculously
expensive
why not do it in other places and i
think that the um
the the downstream effects of american
higher education turning into
something of a laughingstock you know
globally will have
very dire results for um the
comm the the uh the community um
the educational community and and well
beyond of course and well beyond because
at some level
even if you acknowledge as you and i
both did at the top of this discussion
that there is uh plenty of inequity
in the us and that it is not evenly
distributed the fact is
killing the goose that lays the golden
eggs even if those golden eggs are not
evenly distributed it's going to be a
loss for everyone and you know who's
going to lose
worst are the most downtrodden people
the people who
get the shaft every time so yeah this is
an incredibly
foolish squandering of the power and
position that we have
and it's not going to create a better
world
for anybody downstream of it yeah no i
i i am worried to say the least and i
got a two
two year old and a four-year-old which
makes me all the more uh
paranoid yes although that's young
enough
that maybe the dust will have settled
and we'll be on to something
smarter than this by the time you need
to send them into the world
well if something can't continue the way
it's going it won't
yeah well that's uh yeah it's a very
frightening thing you've just said
but uh all right i want to ask you about
a couple last things before i let you go
great um so i want to talk to you about
the observation about the relationship
of what we might have called social
justice warriors
back in 2015 what we might now call
uh wokeness um and
the relationship of that belief system
to cognitive therapy
oh they're just completely incompatible
in what way
well one of uh and it's one of these
things you know
as i explained in my book i had anxiety
and depression cognitive behavioral
therapy
saved my life but as i was studying
cognitive behavioral therapy
it's particularly given what i did it
was blazingly obvious that campuses seem
to be teaching
everybody to engage in these cognitive
distortions and this includes
binary thinking which is either or
thinking mind reading assuming that you
know where someone is coming from
probably the biggest one is over
generalization is a cognitive distortion
and as you're teaching yourself all of
these um
all these habits hold on again wow it
won't turn back on anyway
um as you're teaching yourself all of
these uh habits
particularly working on campus you it
was as if universities and
administrators were saying
do over generalize do engage in binary
thinking and
and they are that's exactly what a lot
of this ideology comes down to
and i think that's actually one of the
reasons why cbt has been shown to be
somewhat less effective with this
generation
because there are too many dogmas that
rely on over generalization
require binary thinking catastrophizing
for example
um so the two uh the the uh cognitive
cognitive behavioral therapy and getting
over cognitive distortions which is also
a better way to argue
a better way to think um a better way to
understand the world better is to try to
address these in yourselves
a lot of the social justice stuff the
most toxic of it relies
on on these things so they're completely
they're like matter and anti-matter
and unfortunately what i see happening
is rather than
um go with the you know the
reality-based approach
um people are rejecting the obvious
lessons of cbt
that's so interesting so
a i find this a very provocative insight
and an important one it fits exactly
with what i've encountered and so many
others have
as well but there is some
incredible process by which
everything functional is being turned on
its head it's almost as if there's some
algorithm
that seeks that which works to
invalidate it
so i remember you know before evergreen
melted down
i remember the first time i was in a
faculty meeting and i
said something about the hazard of what
was taking place
to enlightenment values
i didn't think the idea of enlightenment
values being a good thing
could possibly be controversial in a
room full of academics
but what i got back was pushback that
enlightenment values were
this oppressive system and i was just
stunned the first time i heard it
but um then you know
downstream a couple years and we're
looking at the invalidation
of basic arithmetic we're dealing with
the invalidation
of the idea of a colorblind society
we're dealing with the invalidation of
the idea that there is something
logical that is independent of power
it's just like
every single thing on which you could
start a reboot to some sort of agreement
is being sabotaged right and
you know i think you're what i find so
compelling about your
your point about cognitive behavioral
therapy is that
um you're talking about the basic
ability of the mind to cope
is being sabotaged by an ideology that
is going to make people
weaker more vulnerable more
volatile i mean it's crazy
yeah no it it's and here's and here's
where i actually
because i i work at a job that can make
you very angry
and that's one of the reasons why you
see me compulsively cracking jokes on
on twitter is because it's just like you
know it it it's
it's a coping mechanism but one thing
that i've tried to do since we are
really trying to change the culture
is when i write something i tend to take
out all the all the anger
you know um i get rid of the adverbs you
know i go after everything
um that shows anger but there is one
thing that i am
very angry about and i didn't say in the
book
is we know this generation has higher
levels of anxiety and depression
we know this generation has higher
levels of suicide now i think that some
of that ideology that creeps in earlies
is playing a part in it
but also i think things like you know
the wealth stratification and there's
other other factors at play
but to know that and then have students
show up on your campus and to tell them
i oh yeah i know you have really high
rates of suicide and depression and
self-harm
by the way here's an ideology in which
you are
evil um and you almost all of you
with some exceptions are both oppressed
and oppressors
and there's absolutely nothing you can
do about it other than feel
deep deep guilt guilt and shame you
should isolate yourself from other
people um you you these are your
characteristics you have no locus of
control
you have no individual identity have a
nice day
and there's something really messed up
about particularly when you know these
kids are already coming in
really sad and and really kind of like
suffering to tell them something
that hopeless um but also that you need
to do something about it but you'll
never actually fix it
well i've never i've never seen a sort
of sadder
um less productive ideology i mean
actually no i've seen
i i've seen downright harmful ones but
as far as one that doesn't seem to want
to get you
anywhere you know so like after george
floyd died i i was
you know immediately being kind of like
well there's you know definitely there's
police reform that we definitely need to
do there's
logical steps that we could actually do
to take that we've been meaning to so
maybe this is the chance
and instead that opportunity being
squandered and turned into something
about like
let's get kids kicked out of college
let's get professors in trouble for
faux pas essentially it's like we've
squandered this opportunity to help
people in the real world
um to participate in this weird
pointless sad little dance
yes and in fact uh what we saw
was that students who figured out how to
achieve
were actually socially punished by
their would-be peers for doing so
there's this belief
you know that achievement is itself
you're having capitulated to the system
rather than you empowering yourself
um to do good in the world and
you know i mean you you don't deliver
the punchline of the setup you just
gave but basically you're arguing that
this is going to kill people
that you are taking people who are
already vulnerable because they already
have anxiety and self-doubt and you are
creating an unwinnable circumstance
which is exactly the kind of
um hopeless situation that does lead
people to hurt themselves
and i i agree with you you know i as a
professor i very
keenly felt an obligation to see
students and to help them see
clearly in part because things do look
pretty hopeless until somebody helps you
i don't know navigate the world and
understand where you where you fit in it
and just to see a movement
undoing that kind of work in some sort
of generic blanket across the board
super rapid way is very frightening yeah
yeah and ultimately relying on tactics
to win arguments in dorms in the 1990s
yeah now once you say it you're you're
right about that
all right last question where do you
think we're headed
i hope i was always i always hope the
last question will be uh
how dare you
where do i think we're headed um i'm
definitely
a lot less confident in that prediction
um
that i than i would have been maybe five
years ago
things are going to get worse before
they get better um for sure
i am so optimistic about the upcoming
election
that my family and i are getting out of
dc uh for the entire month of november
um and i love my i love this town like i
i i like dc as a city in its own right
um and
i'm scared about what november is going
to look like and and people like what
specifically
i'm like when you can think of 14
different possible
possible scenarios it might be time to
take your kids and
and go in the short term i think things
are going to be
in the next i'm not looking forward to
the next six months
um if there is a landslide that would
help
um because what certainty one way or
another would help but the idea that we
actually have you know someone saying
a president saying that the the election
is flawed there's going to be
that's going to be radicalizing like the
the old mcvey types you know from the
1990s
who blew up stuff to um so that's going
to be incredibly ugly so basically yeah
i'm i'm predicting things are going to
be
very ugly for the next six months i
don't really know what things are going
to look like
after um after covid uh
the you know i'm super i'm hopeful that
20 20 21
will be a better year i think it almost
statistically has to be
a better year um but you know when it
comes to the
the the long scheme the long scheme of
thing i'm i'm bullish on the human race
um i think as long as we don't kill the
golden goose of
not just of of of um producing wealth
and growth which we desperately need to
keep
which is much more essential to our
society that than people seem to get
um you know particularly in some in some
of these circles
i'm also very excited about you know
technological
progress and i do think the long-term
health of free speech
is better than you would think given all
the all the things conspiring against it
for
one very simple reason that you alluded
to before it works really well
um societies that actually can talk
about their problems
tend to do better but uh for the next
six months
um if i could get i i cropped i cracked
a really long
convoluted joke on twitter about this
about how uh
time travel is possible and we know that
if you can you know get
any fragment of the speed of light you
start actually having noticeable time
shifts and
therefore i'd like the country to take
the sacrifice and move me and my
family into i don't know like may of
next year next year as fast as possible
i like it oh yeah i i agree with you
it seems like there's an awful lot of
potential energy built up in the system
yeah i did i read david french's um book
divided we fall
um and i also have to remind my fellow
left of center people it's like
this is one of the few people who's
right up center who's actually trying so
don't kick him away but he made such a
plausible case for um
uh for the country dividing and
one thing that he did that i think was
really important that people tend to
you know forget is what the consequences
for world peace would be if suddenly the
us were
divided and and the number number one
and two powers
in the world where china and russia yes
uh
so can i ask you um i i have looked at
the map
and unfortunately the cities are kind of
distributed about the place in such a
way that they can't really
secede from the rural parts of the u.s
have you ever noticed this
oh yeah i talk about population density
and how much of how much of a predictor
it is
of uh of where you are politically and
and you're right
um i do think that probably the most
plausible one
would be some kind of like california
secession
was the one that i think would that
seems the most plausible to me
california well geez okay yeah i mean we
talk sometimes
uh i think mostly jokingly about
cascadia
up here but um yeah i i
must say i'm stuck uh with the
recognition that there's not a
geographic
mechanism to divide the country that
solves the
the puzzle as it stands well that's one
of the reasons why i like um
i like david french's closest thing to a
conclusion
which is let's get comfortable with um
federalism again you know essentially
like if the states are going to be this
different let them be that different
you know within the bill of rights of
course um because you know they should
be
obliged by that but you know if
countries if states want to experiment
with everything from health care to as
they already are
you know uh medical marijuana and that
kind of stuff
then we should definitely remember that
we've
you know we've been pretty desperate
before and
as long as you as long as you allow for
something that allows a lot of
internal diversity we can actually
potentially weather it but if we
if we try too hard to to have impose
uniformity we're going to snap
um do you think we could give the woke
revolution
a state or loan it to them and then when
they discover how dangerous what they're
playing with
is maybe we could be generous and
welcome them back and uh
start over i wouldn't wish that upon my
uh darkest enemy
i hear you yeah now that i hear myself
say it's a terrible idea
it's a i mean my my here's my family
story
my great-grandfather was a serf he
bought his way into freedom in 1858 and
immediately
lucianov started doing very well we
became professors and lawyers and judges
and landowners and all this kind of
stuff
we were peasants who made good and in
every any other country that would be
considered commendable
and instead there was an ideology that
my family had been fighting
you know ever since we could read
essentially
that was over simplistic and that was
usually by
intellectuals first generation educated
people and meanwhile the peasants were
like actually i'd like things to be 15
better you know it'd be lovely if i
could own a couple more things and have
some more time off but the
but the intellectuals wanted the perfect
revolution so for example in 1862
um was 62 they assassinated zara
alexander ii
on his way to create a duma on his way
to create a parliament
because these radicals thought that that
wasn't gonna that would
that would be too good and people
wouldn't want their glorious
you know bolshevik revolution at that
point so and so like the progress of
russia was stalled by people who
by by this category of people and they
wanted to shoot people like me and my
family in the back of the head because
we were educated but didn't agree
and that's one of the reasons why we had
to get the hell out of there and i've
seen
what these ideologies can do once they
take on that religious fervor
and having to fight it again
terrifies me um but uh
hopefully you know people will not let
that happen again
hopefully well i have to say i can't
help but hear an
echo of evergreen and so many other
places in what you just described you
know the idea
of uh you becoming a villain because
you're educated and you don't agree
yeah that feels like exactly what
happened um
i will say greg i'm not all that hopeful
about where
we're headed i agree with you about the
danger of what's coming
but i'm uh really pleased to have you on
the right side
absolutely brett and i'm looking forward
to seeing you again
um i'm really i really hate the fact
that we have to miss the professor
conference this year that like
that that's become a highlight of my
year yeah the uh
the restrictions on uh travel and
gathering
are more dangerous than i think people
have yet spotted i mean even just the
fact that americans
are going to be sidelined from
collaborating internationally in person
if you know other parts of the world
figure out how to solve this and we just
decide to give up
yeah um but anyway yes hopefully
hopefully 2021 doesn't decide to teach
2020 a lesson
by being even more dramatic
well real pleasure um let me know when
this is up
and uh you know stay in touch and of
course if you know anybody who gets in
trouble
on campus because i'm sure they come to
you send them to us oh my god you should
see my well you
you don't need to see my inbox because
you've got your own inbox full of the
same stuff i'm sure
okay well thanks greg lucianoff this has
been a real pleasure and very
eye-opening i look forward to our next
meeting and if not that our next
discussion where can people find you
at the fire.org um that's uh my
organization and i also have a blog on
it that's just for me called the
eternally radical idea
the eternally radical idea and people of
course if they haven't read coddling of
the american mind they should
not pass go they should not collect 200
they should go get a copy of this book
and read it immediately
i'm ver i'm very proud of it i'm doing a
series called catching up with coddling
updating the data
um and unfortunately most of the trends
we saw back then are
shockingly worse oh well that's uh
that's not lovely no no no it isn't all
right thanks so much greg
absolutely thanks everyone we'll see you
next time great chat
[Music]
you